Guide to the Jean Dean Cole collection, Circa 1900-1951 MVC0009.MS
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Jean Dean Cole collection
1900-1951
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
MVC0009.MS
2.5 Linear Feet 1 slim document box, 1 document box, 1 map folder
Jean Dean Cole was the third president of Mount Vernon Seminary, founded in Washington, D.C. in 1875. Mount Vernon Seminary and College merged with The George Washington University in 1999. This collection contains correspondence, writings, photographs, and a diploma, of and belonging to Jean Dean Cole, president of Mount Vernon Seminary from 1923 to 1936.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: correspondence and writings and biographical materials.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains photographs, prints, correspondence, writings, and a diploma of and belonging to Jean Dean Cole. The materials range in date from 1900-1951.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Collection acquired by GWU upon merger with Mount Vernon College. Collection transferred to Foggy Bottom campus in 2009.
Biographical / Historical
Jean Dean Cole began teaching at Mount Vernon Seminary in 1905. After the death of Adelia Gates Hensley in 1923, Cole became the third president of the school. During her time as president, the Board of Trustees established the Junior College as a distinct unit. Cole resigned as President in 1936 and died in 1939.
Women's colleges; Women -- Education; Cole, Jean Dean; Mount Vernon Seminary
- Correspondence and writings, 1925-1950; Series 1
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains correspondence written to, from, and about Jean Dean Cole as well as speeches and essays written by her. The material dates from 1925-1950.
  - Correspondence to Allie Edwards and Marjorie Hutton, 1933-1934; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence to, from, and concerning Jean Dean Cole, 1925-1950; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters to Board of Trustees, President reports, Board related correspondence, 1933-1939; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Nebraska Ave. Endowment Fund--carbons of Miss Cole's letters, 1937; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Nebraska Ave. Endowment Fund--list of Miss Cole's addresses and copies of letters, 1937; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Nebraska Ave. Endowment Fund--worksheets in connection with Cole's letters, 1937; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Original typed centenary address--"Elizabeth Somers, Pioneer", 1937; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Typed history of Mount Vernon Seminary by Jean Dean Cole, 1925; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Biographical materials, 1900-1951; Series 2
  Arranged chronologically.
  This series contains photographs of Jean Dean Cole, ephemera regarding her memorial service, and her diploma from Mount Holyoke. The material dates from 1900-1951.
  - Jean Dean Cole diploma from Mount Holyoke, 1900; Series 2 (Map-folder 1)
  - Small photograph, "Miss Cole Senior English", 1908-1909; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Photograph of Alumnae Council in Great Hall at Nebraska Ave., 1936; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Print of Cole in regalia, 1938; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Memorial service ephemera, 1939; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Memorial pamphlet, 1939; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Print of Cole on June calendar page, 1951; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Professional portrait photograph of Cole, undated; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Professional portrait photograph of Cole backed with foam board, undated; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 6)